the topic of learning is a very rich in
学习的主题非常丰富
fascinating one in game theory we will
我们将在博弈论中吸引人
be able to to sort of just get a taste
能够有点品味
for it and we'll be focusing on two
为此，我们将专注于两个
examples of learning in games one one
游戏学习实例一一
one method called fictitious play and
一种称为虚拟游戏的方法
the other called no regret learning and
另一个人称无悔学习和
in Flickr an algorithm called regret
在Flickr中，一种称为后悔的算法
matching but the topic really is vast
匹配，但话题确实很大
and so let me say a few words before we
所以让我先说几句话
actually look at the specific methods
实际看一下具体方法
the first of all we should recognize
首先我们应该认识到
that learning in in in game theory is
在博弈论中学习是
fundamentally different from learning in
根本不同于学习
certain other disciplines for example as
其他某些学科，例如
it's done in machine learning in in in
这是在机器学习中完成的
AI in computer science or in statistics
计算机科学或统计学领域的AI
only optimization in those in those in
只有那些在那些
those disciplines one usually has in
通常有那些学科
mind a single actor acting in an
介意一个演员在
environment when the environment is
当环境是
unknown to the agent it may be
代理人可能不知道
stochastic it may be partially
随机的可能是部分
observable and so it's very difficult to
可观察到的，因此很难
figure out what an optimal strategy is
弄清楚什么是最佳策略
but there is a well-defined notion of
但是有一个明确的概念
optimal strategy and the goal of
最佳策略和目标
learning is to learn something about the
学习是要学习一些关于
environment and how to act best in it in
环境以及如何在其中发挥最佳作用
the case of game theory the environment
博弈论案例环境
includes or perhaps consists entirely of
包括或可能完全由
other agents so even as you're trying to
其他代理商，即使您正在尝试
learn and adapt so are they and so what
学习和适应，他们也是，还有什么
ends up happening is you can't really
最终发生的是你真的不能
divorce the notion of learning from the
脱离学习的观念
notion of teaching because as you adapt
教学的概念，因为随着您的适应
you're influencing the activities of
你正在影响...的活动
other agents and just imagine informally
其他特工，只是非正式地想象
the situation where there are two agents
有两个代理商的情况
who repeatedly drive toward each other
反复相向
playing the game of chicken and maybe a
玩鸡游戏，也许
drag racing by
飙车
lessons and perhaps the one of the one
课程，也许是其中之一
of the so so what they want to do is of
所以他们想做的是
course they want to just zoom straight
当然他们只想放大
ahead and have the others go to the side
向前，让其他人走到一边
of the road and and give them to the
并把它们交给
right of way of course if they both do
当然，如果他们俩都这样做的话
that they collide and that's a bad idea
他们发生碰撞，这是一个坏主意
and so they sort of teach other and over
因此，他们有点教别人
time
时间
dare more or less so you mentioned that
或多或少敢，所以你提到
there's one driver who's an extremely
有一个司机非常
good modeler of the other driver driver
另一个驱动程序驱动程序的好建模者
too and survivor one learns very well
幸存者也学得很好
whatever driver one strategy driver one
无论哪种驱动因素，一种策略驱动因素
will learn what driver two strategies
将学习驱动程序的两种策略
and best respond to it over time we'll
并随着时间的流逝做出最好的回应，我们将
figure it out and be a great great
弄清楚，成为一个伟大的伟大
responder so it seems like you can't do
响应者，所以看来你做不到
any any better than that well imagine
任何比想象中更好的事
how that player two is a sort of a bully
那两位玩家是如何被欺负的
driver who doesn't really model the
不会真正建模的驾驶员
first driver very well but just barrels
第一名车手很好，但是只有桶
ahead enough carrying about the the
提前进行
about the the circumstances perhaps
关于情况
Agria willing to take a few hits here
Agria愿意在这里打几下
and there to scare off the first driver
然后吓跑第一个司机
or what's going to happen is the second
或将要发生的是第二
driver who's a terrible learner and a
一个学习能力很强的驾驶员
very bad modeler of the threat driver is
威胁驱动程序的非常糟糕的建模者是
going to keep going straight ahead and
将继续前进，
the first drive is a wonderful learner
第一个驱动器是一个很棒的学习者
and best responder is going to learn to
最好的响应者将学习
accommodate and what happens is that the
容纳，发生的是
second driver was perhaps a bad learner
二等车手可能是一个不好的学习者
that a very good teacher so that's one
那位非常好的老师
thing to keep in mind when you think
思考时要记住的事情
about learning games and the other is
关于学习游戏，另一个是
that learning is a an overloaded term
学习是一个超负荷的术语
and there are many things you might
你可能有很多事情
learn in the context of games and and
在游戏方面学习和
we'll be looking at a very particular
我们将看一个非常特殊的
slice the context we'll be looking at is
切片我们要看的上下文是
specifically repeated games and when we
特别是重复的游戏以及当我们
speak about learning in repeated games
谈论重复游戏中的学习
will really be speaking about strategies
真的会讲战略
that as they unfold draw interesting
当它们展开时会吸引人
inferences or use the
推断或使用
you might experience in an interesting
您可能会遇到有趣的事情
way that is the nature of learning that
这就是学习的本质
we and in fact most of the literature in
我们以及实际上大多数文献
game theory considers so with that in
博弈论认为
mind here are two examples the first and
请注意，这是两个示例，第一个和
this is perhaps granddaddy of learning
这也许是学习的祖父
regimes in game theory called fictitious
博弈论中的制度被称为虚拟
play in fact it really was not conceived
玩其实不是真的
initially Noor's today viewed as they're
最初，Noor的今天被视为
a realistic or effective learning method
现实或有效的学习方法
but it does contain many of the elements
但它确实包含许多要素
that you see in more involved versions
在更多相关版本中看到的
of learning it was presented first as a
学习它首先被呈现为
heuristic for computing unit computing
计算单元计算的启发式
in Nash equilibrium in games it turns
在游戏中的纳什均衡中
out not to be a very effective procedure
并不是一个非常有效的程序
but it it is an interesting kind of
但这是一种有趣的
basic learning procedure the way it
基本学习程序的方式
works is simply each agent starts with
原理就是每个代理都以
some belief about what is a strategy
关于什么是策略的一些信念
other agent each agent best responds the
其他代理，每个代理最能回应
agent updates their beliefs based on
代理基于以下内容更新其信念
what they observed in the in this
他们在此观察到的
iteration of the game and the game
游戏和游戏的迭代
repeats as I said this is a very general
如我所说，这是很笼统的重复
regime and in fact this is a general
政权，实际上这是一个一般
ream of model based learning we have a
基于模型的学习，我们有一个
model of the agents which you bet
您下注的代理商模型
respond to and update over time
随着时间的推移做出响应并进行更新
fictitious plays is a special case where
虚拟戏剧是一种特殊情况，
the model is simply account of the other
该模型只是对其他模型的解释
agents action so far and you take their
代理商到目前为止的行动，您采取他们的
counts as their current mixed strategy
算作他们目前的混合策略
and so a little more formally let's
所以再正式一点
let's assume that W a is the number of
假设W a是
times the opponent played action a in
对手的动作次数
the past and there's some initial values
过去，还有一些初始值
for those that are nonzero and and then
对于那些非零的，然后
you simply play a with probability that
你只是玩一个概率
is purport
据说
no to the time that it was played to the
没有播放到的时间
play in the past that's a very
过去的比赛非常
straightforward simple procedure
简单明了的程序
yeah so you you always there's something
是的，所以你你总是有东西
a little paradoxical going on because
有点自相矛盾，因为
every agent assuming analyst will talk
每个假设分析师的经纪人都会讲话
about two agents here the two agents are
大约有两个特工这两个特工是
always playing a pure strategy and yet
一直在玩纯粹的策略
they're modeling each other always is
他们互相建模总是
playing a mixed strategy so be that as
采取混合策略，因此
it may and we should also note that you
可能并且我们还应该注意您
need to worry about edge cases such as
需要担心诸如
tiebreaking so what happens if you have
抢七，如果有的话会发生什么
two actions whose will played an equal
两个动作将发挥均等作用
number of times the past well you need
您过去需要的次数
to worry about that here's an example of
担心这是一个例子
how it might work and in the context of
它如何工作以及在以下情况下
matching pennies magic pennies again two
匹配便士魔术便士再两个
players each choosed heads or tails if
玩家各选择正面还是反面
the book shows the same the first guy
这本书显示了第一个家伙
wins if it shows differently the same as
如果它显示与以下内容相同则获胜
AI wins let's assume that these are the
人工智能的胜利让我们假设这些是
initial frequencies that they have in
他们拥有的初始频率
mind
心神
and so eyes beliefs about - is that -
因此，人们对-的信念是-
played heads with you know a frequency
和你打过头
of 1.5 and a entails broadband of
为1.5，需要宽带
frequency - and these are players to
频率-这些是
belief about prayers one okay now it's
关于祈祷的信仰现在可以了
round one what should they do
第一回合他们应该怎么做
well player one wants to bet respond to
好玩家想打赌
his beliefs he believes that this he
他的信念，他相信，这他
believes that this is the distribution
认为这是分布
of player two and he wants to match so
第二个球员，他想比赛
he's gonna play tails they can match
他要打他们可以匹配的尾巴
this is the best response to this mixed
这是对这种混杂的最好反应
strategy that he ascribes put to player
他归因于玩家的策略
two so he's gonna play tails what about
两个，所以他要打尾巴
player 2 player 2 has these beliefs and
玩家2玩家2有这些信念，
he wants to mismatch so since he
他想错配，所以自从他
believes that player 1 will play heads
相信玩家1会发挥正面作用
with greater probability than tails he's
他比尾巴更有可能
gonna play tails so he too is gonna play
要打尾巴，所以他也要玩
tails and the stage is over let's move
尾巴，舞台结束了，让我们继续前进
now to the next stage
现在进入下一个阶段
at this point what happened well these
在这一点上发生了什么这些
are the updated beliefs of the players
是玩家的最新信念
play what observe player to playing
播放观察玩家播放的内容
tales so he increases the two to a three
故事，所以他把两个增加到三个
and so does player two increases his
第二个人也增加了他的
beliefs in what way one will do so what
相信人们将以何种方式行事
do they do well play one still wants to
他们打得还不错吗？
match player two and he still believes
比赛选手二，他仍然相信
in fact even more strongly that player
实际上，那个球员甚至更强大
two will play tail with greater
两个人会打更大的尾巴
probability so he's gonna play tail
概率，所以他要打尾巴
again on the other hand player two now
另一方面，现在有两个玩家
believes that these are the
相信这些是
probabilities so they're to believe that
概率，所以他们要相信
player one will play a tail with a
玩家一会用
greater probability player two one two
玩家二一二的可能性更大
mismatch and so player 2 will now play
不匹配，因此玩家2现在可以玩
heads and you continue this calculation
头，你继续这个计算
and you can persuade yourself that the
你可以说服自己
play will proceed in this fashion and
游戏将以这种方式进行，
this is how fictitious play takes place
这就是虚拟游戏的发生方式
so notice something interesting
所以注意一些有趣的事情
the strategy is don't converge and if
策略是不收敛，如果
you were to continue to play this out
你要继续玩这个
you would see that the t's an agent both
您会看到t既是代理商
sides sort of ebb and flow but you will
双方潮起潮落，但你会
see that there's a certain balance
看到有一定的平衡
taking place over times and this is and
随着时间的推移发生，这是和
and and and and and in fact in this game
and and and and and实际上在这个游戏中
they would converge that on average if
他们平均会收敛
you look the long-term average of the
你看的长期平均水平
strategies each of the ages of play
各个年龄段的策略
tails and heads with equal probability
头和尾等概率
probability 0.5 and so we call this the
概率为0.5，所以我们称其为
empirical frequency now notice that in
经验频率现在注意到
matching pennies 0.5 is also the unique
匹配便士0.5也很独特
Nash equilibrium and the question is is
纳什均衡，问题是
this an accident and the answer is no
这是一场意外，答案是否定的
and here's a theorem theorem says that
这是一个定理定理说
if the empirical frequencies of the
如果的经验频率
players place converge in fictitious
玩家虚拟地融合
play then they have to converge to a
玩，然后他们必须收敛到
Nash equilibrium of the game now the
现在游戏的纳什均衡
maid of conversion general that's why
转换女仆，这就是为什么
it's not an effective learning procedure
这不是有效的学习程序
in general but there are a host of
一般来说，但有很多
conditions under which the even if the
条件，即使
play doesn't converge the empirical
玩不收敛经验
frequency does and here are some of the
频率确实，这是一些
conditions are sufficient if the game is
如果游戏是
zero son if it's solved by something
零儿子，如果有什么解决
called iterative iterated elimination of
称为迭代迭代消除
strictly dominated strategies if it's
严格控制的策略，如果
something called a potential gain which
所谓的潜在收益
we won't define here or if it is a two
我们不会在这里定义，还是两个
by endgame as with one player has only
在残局时，只有一名玩家
two strategies the other may have more
两种策略，另一种可能有更多
but it has what's called generic payoff
但它有所谓的通用收益
Russia also also want to find here but
俄罗斯也想在这里找到
the main thing to do to take away from
要摆脱的主要事情
this is that there are some sufficient
这是有一些足够的
conditions that do they guarantee that
他们保证的条件
the approve empirical frequency of play
批准游戏的经验频率
in fictitious play will converge even
在虚拟的游戏中甚至会收敛
even if the play itself will not let us
即使剧本本身不会让我们
now switch to a very different form of
现在切换到一种非常不同的形式
learning as the whole class will
全班学习
learning called
学习称为
no regret learning and it's different in
不后悔学习，这是不同的
a fundamental way first of all the
最根本的方法
methods themselves will not be modeled
方法本身不会被建模
based they will not explicitly model
基于他们将不会显式建模
what the other agents is doing but
其他特工正在做什么，但是
rather will adapt the the strategy
而是会调整策略
directly that's one difference but
直接是一个区别，但是
perhaps more fundamentally in this case
在这种情况下也许更根本
we will start with a learning method but
我们将从学习方法开始，但是
we start with a criterion for we that we
我们从一个标准开始
want the method to satisfy namely no
想要方法满足即否
regret criterion and so what does this
后悔的标准，这是什么
say
说
we'll say that a regret of an agent at
我们会说一个代理商的遗憾
time T for not having played some
没玩过时间T
strategy is is this difference the
策略是这种差异
difference between that payoff he
他的收益之间的差异
actually got at that time and the payoff
实际上在那个时候得到了回报
he would have gotten
他会得到
had he played strategy yes that's a
他玩过策略是吗
natural enough notion we will now define
我们现在将定义足够自然的概念
when a learning rule exhibits no regret
当学习规则没有后悔的时候
it'll be the key if the case that if in
如果在这种情况下，它将是关键
the limit agents will not play will not
极限特工不会玩不会
exhibit any regrets in other words if
换句话说，表示遗憾
you as you go to the limit the
当您达到极限时
probability with which the regret will
后悔的可能性
tend to zero is one those rules will be
趋于零是那些规则将是一
called no regret learning rules and here
叫无悔学习规则，这里
is one such rule which is surprisingly
是这样的规则之一，这令人惊讶
simple and it's called regret matching
很简单，叫做后悔匹配
and the way it works is as follows it
它的工作方式如下
says simply look at the regret that you
说只要看看你的遗憾
have experienced so far and for each of
迄今为止，每个人都经历过
your pure strategies and pick the pure
您的纯策略并选择纯
strategy in proportionate rest regret so
策略按比例休息感到遗憾
if we define there again again the
如果我们再次定义
regret of the strategy of time t
时间策略的遗憾
authority of s then the probability at
s的权威然后是
the next time that you play is this is
下次您玩的是
the sum of all regrets across all pure
所有纯真的所有遗憾的总和
strategies and take your relative regret
策略，让您感到相对后悔
relative to all it to the sample regrets
相对于所有样本的遗憾
and so a very simple rule and it has
这是一个非常简单的规则
surprisingly strong properties first of
首先具有令人惊讶的强大性能
all is provably exhibit no regret and
一切都证明没有遗憾，
furthermore it actually converges the
而且它实际上收敛了
strategies when you use Norah Graham I
使用诺拉·格雷厄姆一世的策略
regret matching converge to a correlated
后悔匹配收敛到相关
Librium at least for finitely repeated
至少至少有限重复的锂
for finite games games finer games that
对于有限的游戏，更精细的游戏
are repeated so those are two examples
重复，所以这是两个例子
of learning rules
学习规则
one model base specifically fictitious
一个专门虚构的模型库
plate another one that is model free
镀另一个没有模型的
regret matching that exhibit of learning
遗憾地匹配学习的表现
methods that are exhibited no regret as
表现出不后悔的方法
we said in the beginning the topic of
我们在一开始就说过
learning game is a very rich one but at
学习游戏是一个非常丰富的游戏，但在
least we have a taste for it now
至少我们现在有它的味道